Guide to the United States Army 366th Infantry Regiment and other Colored Divisions Collection, ca. 1940-2017
United States Army 366th Infantry Regiment and other Colored Divisions Collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
United States Army 366th Infantry Regiment and other Colored Divisions Collection, ca. 1940-2015
8501
Pratt, James E.
8.5
Motion Pictures, Photographs, publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection contains collected information pertaining mostly to the 366th Infantry Regiment.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
The 366th served with distinction in World War I and II. It faced combat in World War II in Italy with the 92nd Infantry Division. The unit was notable in that, unlike other segregated units, the officers were not white. While many of the members were African American, individuals with dark skin from other ethnicities were also placed with the 366th.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection contains collected information pertaining mostly to the 366th. Includes publications, photographs and video about the regiment, some from Fort Devens, Fort Dix, and Camp Gifu in Kakamigahara Japan. Also an index with photos of tombstones compiled by James E. Pratt of members who were killed in action. Discs of oral histories and presentations conducted by Pratt about the regiment are also included. Also material relating to the rediscovery of a bell given by the 366th found at the Parrocchia Saint Maria Del Carmine in Apulia. Morning Reports for the 366th from March 1941 through March 1945 compiled by Pratt are also included. These reports detail regiment activity before and during combat. Also lists of rosters and payroll for the various companies and units as well as general orders. Also digital files of bios of soldiers from the unit and digital photographs and press coverage from events in Italy in 2017 involving the unit.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Pratt, James E.; United States. Army -- African American troops; Fort Devens (Mass.)
Subjects:
African American soldiers.; Military participation -- African American.; World War, 1914-1918 -- African Americans.; World War, 1939-1945 -- African Americans.
Places:
Fort Devens (Mass.)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Due to the fragility and potential degradation of moving image and sound recordings, viewing and listening is limited to items that have been digitized.
Series I. Books and Documents
Boxes 2-9
Series II. Reproductions of Original Large Format Photographs
Mapcase
Series III. Digital Material
Box 1
Series IV. 8mm Movie Films
Please use DVD copies, not film reels
Box 1
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Books and Documents
  - Soldiers of the 366th Infantry Regiment At Rest In Italy, 2015 (Box 2)
    Document compiled by James Pratt containing photos of gravestones and images of soldiers. Identifying numbers correspond to numbers indicated on copies of photographs included in the collection.
    See the digital version of the bios for the most up-to-date version.
  - Pictorial History 366th Infantry United States Army, Fort Devens, Massachusetts, 1941 (Box 2)
    Formerly owned by Elliotte Johnson Williams. Also a reproduction of the 1941 original.
  - Company I 366th Infantry by Harold E. Russell, Jr., 2008 (Box 2)
    Memoir published by Rosedog Books.
  - No Way Out by Rothacker Smith, 2009 (Box 2)
    The War Story of a WWII Black Buffalo Soldier
  - La Battaglia di Sommocolonia by Dario Giannini and Vittorio Lino Biondi, 2011 (Box 2)
    Includes English translation by Anne Leslie Saunders, Sommocolonia before World War II and The Battle of Sommocolonia.
  - Morning Reports of the 366th Infantry Regiment, March 1941 - September 1942 (Box 2)
    Photo copies of the reports compiled by James Pratt. NARA Approved. These detail activities of the regiment. Some months are broken into multiple parts.
  - Morning Reports of the 366th Infantry Regiment, October 1942 - October 1943 (Box 3)
  - Morning Reports of the 366th Infantry Regiment, November 1943 - June 1944 (Box 4)
  - Morning Reports of the 366th Infantry Regiment, June 1944 - December 1944 (Box 5)
  - Morning Reports of the 366th Infantry Regiment, January 1945 - March 1945 (Box 6)
  - Roster and Payroll lists for Service Company, Regimental Band, Officers, 1941 - 1943 (Box 6)
  - Roster and Payroll lists for Anti-Tank, Cannon, Company A, B, C, D, E, F, G, 1941 - 1943 (Box 7)
  - Roster and Payroll lists for Company H, I, K, L, M, Headquarters and Regiment, Battalion 1, 2, 3, Medical Detachment., 1941 - 1943 (Box 8)
  - General Orders, 1941 - 1945 (Box 9)
  - Court Martial of Louis P. Sheppard, December 25, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Court Martial of Orville Phoenix, February 6-7, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Court Martial of William Gilliard, February 16, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Court Martial of Sellers Judkins Jr., March 13, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Court Martial of Hermon Streeter, April 6, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Court Martial of Shafter Roberts, March 11, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Court Martial of Wilson C. Williamson, August 21, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Court Martial of Charles Adkins, November 23, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Court Martial of General Lee Grant, January 8, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Court Martial of Mansfield Spinks, January 16, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Court Martial of Anna C. Morrison, Mary E. Green, Alice E. Young, and Johnnie Murphy, March 10, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Court Martial of Charlie Ervin Jr., July 30, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Materials relating to a talks and events surrounding a visit by family members of those who served in the 366th to Italy in 2017., 2017 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    Includes coloring book that has an image of the bell from Parrocchia Saint Maria Del Carmine in Apulia.
  - History of the 366th Infantry Regiment for the month of November 1944, November 1944 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - History of the 366th Infantry Regiment for the month of December 1944, December 1944 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - History of the 366th Infantry Regiment for the month of January 1945, January 1945 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - History of the 366th Infantry Regiment for the month of February 1945, February 1945 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Operations Instructions 366th Infantry Regiment, February - September 1943 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Field Orders 366th Infantry Regiment, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Field Orders 366th Infantry Regiment, November - December 1944 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Special Orders 366th Infantry Regiment, January 1-31, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Investigation of Combat Activities 1st Battalion 366th Infantry Regiment, February 3-23, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Investigation of Combat Activities 2nd Battalion 366th Infantry Regiment, February 10-28, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Report of Operations of the 3rd Battalion 366th Infantry Regiment, February 8-11, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Series II. Reproductions of Original Large Format Photographs
  Originals remain in the possession of the collector.
  - Officers of the 366th Infantry, Fort Devens, Massachusetts, May 16, 1941 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    Original from Thurston Jamison.
  - Company B 366th Infantry, Fort Devens Massachusetts, May 1941 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    CRobert W. Hainsworth, commanding. Original from Thurston Jamison.
  - Company I 366th Infantry, Fort Devens Massachusetts, August 1941 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    Captain Emerson J. Pierce, commanding. Original from Harold Russell.
  - Company D 366th Infantry, Fort Devens Massachusetts, August 1941 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    Captain Frederick O. Petite, commanding. Original from Charles Pratt.
  - First Service Command Tactical School Class 27, Publick House, Sturbridge, Massachusetts, April 1943 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    Original from Charles Pratt. Also a 2nd copy with individuals numbered for identification.
  - First Service Command Tactical School Class 28, Publick House, Sturbridge, Massachusetts, May 1943 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Company D 366th Infantry, Fort A. P. Hill, November 1943 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - Cannon Company 366th Infantry, Fort A. P. Hill, Virginia, November 1943 (Mapcase-folder 1)
    Original from Frank Cloud.
- Series III. Digital Material
  - Digital files (Box Estorage)
    Biographies and digitized photographs of many of the soldiers. Also news coverage and media associated with a 2017 events in Italy with family members of those who served in the 366th, including an event in Sammichele di Bari where the soldiers bought a bell for the church.
  - The Dangerous Missions Collection, 2002; 1208-1211 (Box 1)
    Includes a segment on the 366th.
  - Buffalo Soldiers, WWII Home Movies, 2008; 1212 (Box 1)
    By VFA. Home movies of the 366th Infantry Regiment shot at Fort Devens from 1943-1944. CDV title incorrectly refers to them as Buffalo Soldiers.
  - Presentation on the 366th by James Pratt at the Fort Devens Historical Society, November 9, 2013; 1213 (Box 1)
  - 366th Infantry Regiment Various Photos, 2014; 1214 (Box 1)
    High quality scans of photographs, some used in the creation of the reproductions within the collection.
  - Interview with Harold E. Russell Jr., January 2014; 1215 (Box 1)
    Also includes digital photographs.
  - Presentation on the 366th by James Pratt at the Publick House, Sturbridge, Massachusetts, May 15, 2014; 1216 (Box 1)
    At War in New England, the 366th Infantry Regiment in WWII.
  - Presentation on the 366th by James Pratt in North Yarmouth Maine, May 17, 2014; 1217 (Box 1)
  - Interview with Harold Smith a member of the 92nd Infantry who served in Italy in World War II., 2015; 1220 (Box 1)
  - Digitized copies of the movie films from Karen Jamison, including Fort Devens and footage from Japan. Please use these DVDs instead of the film reels listed below., 1222-1225 (Box 1)
- Series IV. 8mm Movie Films
  Titles are taken from the cans of film, the titles may not be 100% accurate of what is depicted. The films may also have had multiple original reels spliced together to form a new reel. Digitization was done by an outside vendor and placement on DVDs, which may not be in the same order as the reels listed below.
  Please use DVD copies, not film reels.
  - Fort Devens, Koko, Ashtrid, Maine, Fort Dix?, 1941; 1076 (Box 1)
    Jamison reel 1. Digitized on DVD-1222
  - Fort Devens, Mac, ?, Davies, S, Club etc., Pet ?, 1077 (Box 1)
    Jamison reel 2 Digitized on DVD-1222
  - Colonel Jim Robinson at ?, 1078 (Box 1)
    Jamison reel 8. Digitized on DVD-1222
  - Fort Devens, Training B Company, 1941-1942; 1079 (Box 1)
    Jamison reel 13. Digitized on DVD-1223
  - Mt. Fuji Japan and Fort Dix, Undated; 1099 (Box 1)
    Jamison reel 3. Digitized on DVD-1224
  - Seattle Washington, 1947; 1100 (Box 1)
    Jamison reel 4. Digitized on DVD-1224, DVD-1225. Also has a stag film titled "A Model Must Please" spliced in that shows women in their underwear from 1942.
  - Boat Trip to Japan on the S. S. Republic. Color, 1948?; 1101 (Box 1)
    Jamison reel 5. Digitized on DVD-1224
  - Gifu Japan. Color, 1948-1950; 1102 (Box 1)
    Jamison reel 6. Digitized on DVD-1224
  - Camp Gifu Japan, 1947-1950; 1103 (Box 1)
    Jamison reel 7. Digitized on DVD-1225